Register of the Mikhail Mikhailovich Kostenko papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Mikhail Mikhailovich Kostenko papers
1892-1972
1904-1928
2006C42
Hoover Institution Archives
2 manuscript boxes, 2 oversize boxes, 1 oversize folder (1.6 linear feet)
Correspondence, personal and military documents, photographs, and memorabilia relating to Russian military operations in the Russo-Japanese War and World War I and to Russian émigré activities. Includes some later family correspondence.
Kostenko, Mikhail Mikhailovich, 1881-1928.
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 2006.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Related Collection(s)
Pavel Aleksandrovich Bazarov papers, Hoover Institution Archives
Biographical Note
1881 Born in Russia
1899 Joined the Russian Imperial Army
1901-1904 Road and topographical surveying in Manchuria (Northeast China) for Russian military
1904 Fought in Russo-Japanese War
1907-1912 Road and topographical surveying in Japan
1914-1916 Fought in World War I as an aviation officer and promoted to Colonel in the 8th Siberian Mountain Artillery of the Russian Imperial Army. Decorated with St. George's Military Cross
1918 Applied through the United States Embassy in Japan for permission to join the American Expeditionary Forces (AEF)
1920 Immigrated to the United States
1922-1928 Map draftsman for Rand McNally & Co. and South American division of the American Geographical Society
1928 Died in New York City, NY
Scope and Content of Collection
This collection documents the military career of Mikhail Mikhailovich Kostenko during the Russo-Japanese War and World War I, as well as his post-war immigration to the United States. The collection includes family documents, military records, correspondence, photographs, and memorabilia.
The Biographical File relates mainly to Kostenko's life in the United States, and includes identification documents, naturalization records, and family records. In particular, there is collected correspondence and genealogical information gathered by Kostenko's son, Barry (Boris) Kostenko.
The Military Career File relates to Kostenko’s military career and Russian military operations, especially in Japan between 1904 and 1920, and consists of reports, orders, certificates, sketches, and maps.
The Photographs are mostly from Kostenko's time spent stationed in Japan, and Memorabilia consists of medals, badges, ribbons, military adornments, and map draftsman tools.
Russia. Armiia--Officers; Russians--United States.; Russo-Japanese War, 1904-1905.; World War, 1914-1918--Campaigns--Eastern Front.
- Biographical File, 1904-1972
  Scope and Contents note
  Contains personal correspondence, family documents, and naturalization records detailing Kostenko's personal life and immigration to the United States. Arranged alphabetically by subject.
  - Correspondence, 1892-1972
    - Family postcards, 1892-1931 (Box-folder 1: 1)
    - Family correspondence between Kostenko's sister Lidia Alekseeva (Lydia Alexeiff) and Barry (Boris) Kostenko, 1907-1972 (Box-folder 1: 2)
  - Family documents, 1920s
    - Death certificate, 1928 August 21 (Box-folder 1: 3)
    - Genealogical document, 1929 September 10 (Box-folder 1: 4)
    - Research notes by Barry Kostenko, undated (Box-folder 1: 5)
    - Marriage records, 1925 (Box-folder 1: 6)
  - Identification, membership, and business cards, post 1915 (Box-folder 1: 7)
  - Immigration records, 1914-1927
    - Commendations of Kostenko's service in World War I from US Army, 1921 (Box-folder 1: 8)
    - Translation of military service record, immigration declaration, and Certificate of Naturalization, 1920-1927 (Box-folder 1: 9)
  - Personal notes, bonds, and account book, 1914-1924 (Box-folder 1: 10)
  - Prayer book, undated (Box-folder 1: 11)
  - South American travel documentation for American Geographical Society, 1924 (Box-folder 1: 12)
- Military Career File, 1904-1919
  Consists of military appointments, orders, certificates, reports, sketches, and maps depicting activities of the Russian military during the Russo-Japanese War and World War I, as well as Kostenko's military service as a surveyor and aviation officer. Arranged by subject.
  - Military career record, undated (Box-folder 2: 1)
  - Service reports, appointments, orders, and travel papers, 1904-1919 (Box-folder 2: 2-3)
  - Artillery sketches and tables, undated (Box-folder 2: 4)
  - Maps and plans, 1907-1915 (Map case)
- Photographs, 1904-1918
  Photographs related to Kostenko's military career, especially his training in aviation school, the Russo-Japanese War, and his travels throughout Japan. Arranged by format.
  - Kostenko in aviation school, 1906-1914 (Box-folder 2: 5)
  - Russo-Japanese War, 1904-1905 (Box-folder 2: 6)
  - Photo album, 1904-1918 (Box 4)
- Memorabilia, undated (Box 3)
  Consists of medals, badges, ribbons, military adornments, compasses, and draftsman tools.